[Music]
so the film coming up is a three-way
conversation between me Daniel Thorson
of the emerged podcast and Josh fields
who's the CEO of consciousness hacking
and it's on the topic of existential
risk and collapse which is something
daniel has been covering a lot on his
podcast and josh has also been delving
really deeply into it as he'll outline
in the film and it was recorded a little
while ago a couple of months ago during
the extinction rebellion protests in
London but it feels like the right time
to release it now and it's hard to
imagine a more important topic but also
one that's really hard to grasp and in
some ways quite paradoxical which is
what I try to outline in the first part
of the film at the same time that that
we we are talking about collapse and
there are these kind of very convincing
arguments very convincing models it's
still the case that for most people on
the planet this is the best time yet to
have been alive and in terms of wealth
in terms of quality of life and all
those things like that's something that
I'm kind of very conscious about putting
a flag in early because I know that our
audience quite rightly some of them can
be very kind of reactive to that the
whole idea of it because especially the
sort of the original Peterson audience
Jordan Peterson audience because he he
talks a lot about that like that we're
not we're nowhere near grateful enough
for the achievements of Western
civilization and etc etc how do you hold
that kind of tension that that is that
is probably the deepest paradox of our
times right is this M Steven Pinker
enlightenment truth that that's held by
a lot of these thinkers at Peter
Diamandis Steven Pinker that we are in
an exponential age of progress and
Samuel taneous Lee Roy collapsing and
simultaneously you know we were
desecrating ecosystems so life
expectancy is almost doubled since 1900
almost the whole world is illiterate and
child mortality is reduced by 50% since
night since since 1990
and yet there seems to be coming the
cost of the very planet we call home and
so this is the thing like I think we're
the left go wrong as they say you know
we're in this like terrible terrible
disease like kami apocalyptic times and
it's all humanity's fault and what a lot
of that narrative misses is that we've
were also in in the best times that's
something that I struggle really really
struggle to hold and they call that the
environmentalist paradox but both are
true gen bando holds a truth Steven
Pinker holds a truth one is a claps
ologist and a catastrophist the other is
precisely and I just think what is being
called for here is some sort of
synthesis that sees these truths as only
half true and that we have to find a way
through into this you know really really
celebrating progress while also being
realistic as to the implications of said
progress yeah yeah I resonate a lot with
that and I think the danger in any case
is from my perspective sort of
collapsing into certainty like we know
how it's going to go we know that it's
going to be a kind of catastrophic
collapse or we know that it's gonna be
you know exponential beauty for the rest
of time I think both of those
perspectives seem quite dangerous to me
if you hold on to it with certainty so
really that's the kind of rub of it for
me and we've talked about this before
Joshua it's like yeah can we can we hold
both of those perspectives without
needing the easy certainty that either
could offer if it's held in the wrong
way and which for this question to both
of you which what's the most convincing
model or evidence or narrative that
you've seen that persuades you that the
collapse narrative is true for people
maybe who haven't been exposed to it or
you know delves deeply into it sure you
guys have so um I I started researching
for a thesis at at CI is and what are
the parallels between
predicament and civilizations have gone
before and I think there are three
really and simple mechanisms that are
very self-evident in our current
situation that are also implicit in the
literature as to what some of the causes
of collapse have been in the past the
vs. purely environmental degradation
if you look Jared Diamond and whose is
the kind of magnum opus on this but
societies and civilizations that come
out of alignment with their natural
ecosystems our societies that are
destined to fail so we have
environmental degradation as one
mechanism we have complexity as another
at this Joseph tinters work I'm not
going to go into them but if you look at
our complexity situation just now is
exponential complexity linear competence
the more of these two curves the couple
with the higher the probability we're
not going to be able to make sense of
that complexity and then the third is
inequality so if you look at there's
various models that show how stable or
unstable society is and and if you enter
there's one motor called handi hndy and
really these models are just indicators
of systemic instability and equality
being a huge variable and where we are
just now with inequality I think M is
pretty easy to see so this combination
of environmental degradation excess
complexity and excess inequality are
three very very clear mechanisms that
have led to collapse in the past and
they are being expressed in fortitude
and intent and so with such clarity in
our current predicament
I have oscillated between and being an
inevitable assist and a utopianist to
some degree techo save us or were all
doomed and to go to your point I think
the the quality of consciousness that
I've attempted to start to cultivate
there's one of uncertainty how do we
provide how do we maintain stability
with another uncertainty yeah yeah
I guess I everyone's proxying their
sense-making to someone or something at
some level and in this debate unless
you've gone deeply into the kind of the
original research that everyone and I
guess if I was kind of to bring a sort
of skeptical perspective that I'm
holding as well is I'm very skeptical of
the range of certainty like we're
surrounded at the moment where were
recording this in London extinction
rebellion that's going on and I have a
sort of deeply ambivalent relationship
to extinction rebellion I think it's
fantastic that a movement has kind of
come from always nowhere and as making
environmental collapse such a such a
feature of the political landscape while
at the same time I'm concerned that it
seems to be collapsing a very complex
narrative into a very simple one and
also I'm also concerned about the
particular actions that they're urging
to be taken and whether they will be
effective but but what I'm what I'm more
skeptical of I think is something like
extinction rebellion the sort of
environmental catastrophes room that
we're seeing at the moment just seems to
map so perfectly on to kind of a deep
religious substructure of Armageddon sin
repentance all of all of these things
just seem so tight so deeply kind of
woven into thee yeah the mythological
substructure about thinking that the the
fact that it maps on so even even like
the Greta thumbr kind of child prophet
it's it's just it's so and I would have
more I don't see many people in these
environments saying acknowledging that
like I think you have to at least
acknowledge that before you can say yes
it does seem to map on to all of these
things but at the same time we think
that the that this is different for some
reason or whatever do you have any
concerns about that kind of framework
so there's a couple of things the first
is the first piece is you you're
skeptical of the reductionism right that
there's this ko4 and then and this is
the problem with a lot of the climate
movement is that if we just stay below
the 2 degree mark the the 2 degree mark
of warming her veiny part part part of
carbon per in the atmosphere will
somehow save things that for me is an
expression of an ontology that is about
to be left behind which is scientific
materialism that we can understand the
universe and reality by chopping it up
into small parts identifying they may be
a certain variable that is wrong yeah
solving for that variable so for though
complex system yeah I know you've had
Jordan Daniel on this this this very
important difference between complexity
and complicated systems the two-degree
reductionist framework that extinction
rebellion greta throneburg willem are
advocates of it said it's materialist
thinking it's reductionist materialist
thinking so linear as well in an
effectively nonlinear system yeah I mean
the IPCC are trying to caring for
non-linearity are in their in their in
their predictions it's just too
simplistic yeah but what's I guess I'm
left with a question of like what is the
alternative for a mass movement is there
alternative and if not is there no rule
for this kind of mass uprising in
consciousness cuz I'd pay yeah I don't
really see how that would function with
the kind of complexity lens like the
problem is everywhere in nowhere
yeah but you catch the problem you can't
have a mass movement that doesn't have a
defined like extinction rebellion has to
have a defined set of demands you can't
get people out onto the streets to
protest if you don't have a defined set
of up demands well you can but then like
occupy udders in 2008 be dead but they
didn't be had people are in the streets
without they just like change the system
and then I've got nowhere because
they're wearing any clarified objectives
yeah well it did expand the Overton
Window which allowed things like minimum
wage to go up and people to fight for
other policy
is that you know we're quite good so I
think I think it's my sense is that it's
easy to demand too much of something
like extinction rebellion hmm right and
I often you know it's it's important
emember something like you know Rosa
Parks refusing to sit down on the bus
and the actual civil rights legislation
were years apart right these kind of
things move in very nonlinear ways
consciousness kind of works itself into
reality in complex ways right and so we
can't
I don't expect extinction rebellion to
like solve the world but I also see that
it's pointing us in a direction that
it's very important and this this piece
of it the mythological and the
architecture and it's Sauron first of
all a pushback and first of all why is
that problematic okay like just because
it is some sort of like there's a kind
of it's M matching RI archetypal
frameworks and we're projecting
archetypes onto reality whatever else
and I don't know if that's a bad thing
and second of all I think it's also it's
points to a deeper truth that we are
living in deeply methodological times
like this loss of truth from public
discourse Trump Boris this scaled level
of deceit this is like there are the
number of texts that have spoken to the
importance of truth and what happens
when truth is lost in the myth you know
this is Sodom Gomorrah stuff this is you
know the loss of the Aryans for
supposedly because of the loss of truth
and Sir John glob a British historian
wrote in 1972 that just prior to
civilizations collapsing they lose
values like truth so I think there is a
mythological substructure to our current
predicament yeah and I don't necessarily
know what is anything that's for a
reason I'll see one of the enter that
though wreck tarnis speaks about and the
apocalypse archetype and that perhaps
that if we are able to actually go
through apocalypse internally in the
psyche we don't actually have to play
out an external world and this is this
cold yeah this cozy consciousnesses and
this is my big interest is conscious
are we able to integrate that Apocalypse
archetype internally and if so yeah how
does that play out in the dynamics of of
the world yeah and before it has to
happen materially right because in in
the work of James Hillman I recently had
a conversation with Zak's time focused
on this you want it to happen James
Hillman is the Jungian analyst who sort
of one of the most creative as might
have Paul since since um mm-hmm
yeah national psychology but he wrote a
book called suicide and soul and the
idea there is that you want to encourage
on the level of metaphor archetype and
consciousness so that it doesn't have to
be rarified into the material in the
organic I think that's exactly what
you're pointing to and it's why I see
that our Co title function of something
like extinction abelian is actually
being good necessary even in order to
provide for the context in which the
transformation can happen collectively
hmm I guess my my point would be if
you're asking sort of why does it matter
or whether it's a good thing or not is
that my my concern is that if we're
playing out of these these roles but
they've been Miller net Miller
millenarian panics before like there was
one around the turn of the first
millennium like there was enough we had
another one the y2k bug you could argue
as a sort of similar like like we're
very prone to these kind of apocalyptic
movements or thoughts that seem to be
very deeply rooted and are obviously I
mean there was nucleus it gets because
they're in Christian mythology you've
got the whole we don't know when when
we're actually in the Book of
Revelations and there's a there's a
whole sub sector of that like rapture
mythologies and revelation mythologies
that we and Jamie wheal talks about that
the talk is gonna be giving in a couple
of weeks time is actually called recap
to the rapture from the kind of Silicon
Valley rapture theologians you might say
and then the Christian theologians that
Isis like that there's a lot of this
kind of thinking around but how do we
know that this one is different from the
that this this bit this belief pattern
seems common to many different groups
and I think it's certainly more more
mainstream Guardian reading middle-class
to be in the climate cult than in one of
the other cults but there's very similar
similar dynamics in a lot of these cut
these sort of belief systems completely
and I think that's an important piece to
point out is that there is a meaning
crisis and as a as a result of that
meaning crisis what better a an excuse
to to to inject meaning than the end of
the worlds we can see of humanity and we
have a hero leading us call grete like
this is deeply methodological agreed
yeah at the same time there is some
decent science to support this but also
at least in my own studies that even the
theory itself even without the empirics
of exponentially extractive technology
in a limited ecosystem cannot sustain
itself in our current model but but I
think it's it's sir there's something
very clear there's a very clear
connection between this desperation for
meaning and this fitting that jigsaw
puzzle really well and our collective
psyche and is there in it do you have is
there a sense that that's a problem from
your perspective as I see that too and
and you know I think that's actually
very compelling it's certainly a part of
how I construct my meaning in my life is
around this time that we live in that it
could very well be perhaps is and I can
act as if it's an age of transition and
if that doesn't in amplify the
meaningfulness of my human life
Davis point is though that if that does
that make it true
because it's satisfying some
meaning-making longing does it make it
true yeah I mean this is you mentioned
the meaning crisis and this is this is
something that's very very hard to talk
about because of because there's a lot
that was the backlash against the grete
speech and then there was the sort of
backlash against that and anyone who was
sort of seen to criticize or at least
question her role was seen as kind of
could all of these you know angry men
getting upset by a sixteen year old
child and this was a very strange
dynamic but it's very true just even
looking at her own words and a parent's
words
the solution to Greta's personal meaning
crisis is the crusade that she's on now
like they say that she's she I mean if
you if you look at the the level of
difficulty and dysfunction in her family
and her personally because real really
help with her and her sister growing up
and they finding this cause has given
her kind of a real purpose and a real so
there is something about the meaning
crisis playing out in this and also
there's the sense of uneasiness about
what is personal and what is collective
because I I'm pretty sure I haven't read
the book but I've read a review of it
that the narrative inside the thumb book
household was if the world was sort of
den Greta would be fine all the children
were we find that they're just basically
acting out the trauma of the world
rather than the personal trauma of the
family and everything I know about
personal growth and psychology says that
that's not the case so there's also this
kind of deep concern about what is like
with that with activists more generally
like what is personal trauma being
projected out into the world and what is
the world calling for in terms of action
and there's a huge dynamic I mean
there's and multiple different
motivations for lots of different people
involved in these movements as well like
you wouldn't say that everyone involved
in extinction rebellion is traumatized
and protected out onto the world but
there is a there is certainly a dynamic
yeah yeah yeah yeah and I think it's
important to remember even when I
reflect on my time with Occupy Wall
Street which I organized with in New
York City
it's like it's so easy to provide a kind
of unifying narrative of what that was
or what XR is but it too is a complex
phenomenon like if you go down there it
is complicated or no it's not
complicated complex right it's like very
self-organizing it's very immersion
everybody there has different reasons
different things that are calling them
forth even the meaningfulness that they
get from being there is different for
seemingly just about everybody yeah
there are family resemblances but it's
you can't reduce it into a single
perspective or you know kind of way of
seeing what it is that it is happening
to me is more interesting than trying to
offer some kind of interpretation of it
right what why is it being called forth
now and I think that speaks into the
archetypal piece and I also don't really
yeah see it as a problem I mean with
Greta I think that what that speaks to
to me is is anytime that we put somebody
else up on a pedestal be it Greta or
Daniel Sh Malcolm Berger or Jordan
greenhalgh or Jordan Peterson or Bonita
Roy we are stepping outside of I think
what the world is asking for us to do
right now which is step into our own
sense making and become an agent unto
ourselves that can move forward in a way
elsa postal yeah build ourselves on a
pedestal yeah yeah there's a way in
which I believe that to be true yeah I'm
also concerned about this kind of
reduction of the complex bio system
strains into one single variable of
global warming and climate like that
that's that seems to me the most
unsolvable and unmeasurable part of the
whole picture and what it also does it
rejects that well why why do we have
capitalism and why you know if if it was
easy as just taxing the hell out of
carbon and reducing fossil fuels why
don't we just do
we don't do it as your my food your food
your shelter our water is completely
dependent upon the system remaining kind
of like it is and you saw that there's
young vests and France protesting last
year that was over attacks a few okay
that was attacks and fuel and it led to
complete and utter panarchy in the
streets of Paris for days on end so it's
not quite as simple as saying we can
like rapidly reduce carbon to Net Zero
by 2025 and somehow things will be
sorted because the the the the Qatar the
tragedy of duality is that that will
then bring about its own social
catastrophe yeah so we're just we're
kind of stuck between a rock and a hard
place
um skip my mind what I was gonna say
before but um in terms of you sing
before Daniel that really stepping into
the world by their own sense making
capacitively and really not proxying
leadership too much to other people what
the what really trying on claps has felt
like to me I I went through reading the
literature and going into a little bit
of like panic and like we're
moving into hopelessness and apathy but
then eventually what happened and as I
then started to digest this process of
grief and rather than there's like
nothingness that was kind of embody that
was kind of embody in this hopelessness
the other side of grief definitely feels
and felt and feels more like a call to
action that is clean it's you know those
coffees yeah I used coffees you go for
with people who you don't really want to
go for they kind of like the trivial
things do you say yes there's some
social conformity trying on claps as an
archetype and really feeling its
implications can actually lead to I
think a very healthy and positive
response it's not all catastrophizing
that may just be a necessary
intermediary step to get to the clean
face transition by which we want to
America
yeah I think that's really well said and
that was what was occurring to me to
David as you were speaking is that there
is a kind of there are different ways to
hold this archetype and I think that or
this kind of way of seeing and we might
look it and talk more specifically about
the difference in maturity that
different manifestations are holding
this with right and so I noticed too in
the way that I've been related to
collapse look what I found is that it
causes me to reinvest myself into my
community into those around me it offers
a kind of clarifying energy to not spill
my energy into the world in ways that
don't serve my local context really and
and you know I can walk through
extinction rebellion as I've been kind
of exploring it over the last couple of
days and I can see some people are
holding this and it's causing them to
panic it's causing them to freak out and
there are others who are holding it and
it's causing them to kind of step into
themselves go on a kind of hero's
journey to become more heroic through
extinction rebellion and so it's serving
these both these purposes at once for
different people and at least in my
experience the panic was the
intermediary stage to the century yeah
yeah I feel I feel that same sense of
alignment personally in that same sense
of kind of need to step up to be equal
to the times and I felt it from the
moment that pretty much from the moment
the Trump was elected it was like
because I didn't just see quite clearly
how like I'm a foreign affairs
journalist originally by by vocation and
I could just see okay all of these all
the things that were put in place after
the Second World War to kind of keep to
keep the peace from the UN to NATO to
yeah what to all all of these
international organizations Trump was
going to demolish all was going to to go
so individualist that we were back to
the age of sort of great
our politics in a multipolar world and
that that was so that was a kind of
maybe an information of collapse like I
think we're still we still have yet to
see it play out but I look at all of
these different vectors from the
politics to the environment or to all of
these different things I think part of
the narrative this is my other I don't
want to just kind of feel like we're
focusing solely on extinct and rebellion
here but in this instant instance of it
what I feel is the collapse is so multi
very even so pervasive and it's also
interesting that extinction rebellion
has happened in the UK where I think our
political system is going through this
sort of death experience like a real
national breakdown in many ways is like
we're picking up this this sense of
collapse through so many different areas
of our lives and join Green Hall says
you can even look at it in Hollywood
movie it's like you're running there
just things are running out of Road in
all these different ways because we've
we're just running out of different ways
to well all the roads are being played
out at the same time so that's my other
concern with something like extinction
rebelling or something like an activist
response to this time as it's gonna its
taking this this whole dynamic of the
system and collapsing it into one
particular narrative carbon for example
and and and it's time to like yet just
to be able to send all the different
ways that things are coming to the end
at the same time is is something I think
that's really something I'm drawn to and
that that's all
at that exact point is Mike pushback to
people who are acclaimed skeptics is
that they see the planetary boundary
framework don't believe the plan exists
they don't hate if you think that it's
not even real yeah the planetary
boundary framework and from the
Stockholm resilience Center identifies
nine planetary boundaries and if one if
humanity breaches one of those
boundaries earth according to this model
is no longer a safe operating system for
humanity climate change is one of those
boundaries right we've already passed
four of them others you know
others are like you know biodiversity
and so if you look at you don't just
have to be looking at climate change to
know that things are fundamentally wrong
the complexity of our institutions that
are our inability to actually make
decisions and our political systems like
these are all symptoms of much much
deeper structural issues yeah and also
for example the biodiversity one's a
really interesting one because you're
looking at the effect of pesticides
you're looking at the effect of I look
at like the mental health crisis another
one it's like the the materialist
paradigm that does not appreciate living
systems at all and has been kind of
imposing this very simplistic
mechanistic narratives on so many areas
of our planet as is is probably the
closest to sort of that the root cause
of a lot of things we're seeing it's
like the medical one is like the mental
health the catastrophe of mental health
and in the West it's just astonishing
addiction levels and this is also deeply
interlinked so the mental health crisis
for me it's the crisis of trauma to a
large degree and people are feeling
depressed and anxious because their
nervous systems are unable to handle the
the intensities of modern life and most
of our coping mechanisms are to go numb
to the pain is too much to handle too
much to hold and I think part of our
numbness part of the the implications of
our numbness is that we are dead to the
living systems by which we partake we
are dead to the damage we're doing to
the environment we're dead to the damage
we're doing to each other and I think
it's also this there's a loss sometimes
I just like to look around in like this
sometimes I just feel like this lack of
vitality mmm it's like life force life
isn't navigating its way or through us
as living systems or through our living
systems as a whole in a way that it that
that it wants to
there's a deadening and I think this is
really what's being cold for it's like
this transitions into a transition of
you don't see many of beasts animals
unless they've been right pretty abused
investigates and abused like that the
natural world is self itself or
depressed animals I mean it's just a
human yeah yeah well there's also I
think what you're putting to Joshua is
that there are other ways of knowing
right that we've also lost access to I
think this is what you're saying there's
been a kind of like mono culturing of
our epistemologies that you know it's
but you have to have a conversation like
is it true that collapse is happening
can I really believe it but like after I
said a retreat and then I walk into the
cities like the streets of New York City
which I've done before I wouldn't
recommend it it's very overwhelming
you can if you listen to yourself in a
different way you could be like this is
there's something not right here there's
something that's not working here like
and that can give that offers me a
different way in to understanding the
dynamics that are at play right now and
that we don't trust that but we're like
oh no that's just a feeling this this is
the this is I think again this the
paradigm shift that has to come when
people speak about the rise of the
feminine hippie language what it quite
simply is is the M the the understanding
that rational abstraction is only a
single way of knowing and the really the
parts of our bodies that know mmm that
our studio with our survival aren't
abstract it's it's a very deep somatic
way of being and I think what modern
culture has done it's either condemned
them it's like girly weak or just not as
accurate a sense making mechanism and in
so doing has actually shut us off
because ultimately this is the thing if
we knew what we were doing we would stop
but in order to know you can't just
think it has to be felt
and I think and I feel that this is
where a lot of the action isn't isn't
taking place it's because we're still at
this level of reason and reason is
failing I mean look at this is this club
sub sense-making we've lost this
postmodern you know relativism means
reason isn't even cutting anymore it has
to come back to the body has come back
to feeling I'm interested to come back
to the trajectory you talked about
before that you had become very very
pessimistic but you're all not so
pessimistic anymore do you wanna explain
why why why and why so when i when i
read a deep adaptation and i get deep
into the catastrophes lens it's a very
convincing narrative right when i feel
the damage it's a very convincing felt
experience but according going back to
my earlier point is i my senses these
are partial perspectives and the partial
perspective of the catastrophist
is that ignores it ignores what
exponential technology actually means
that to use daniel trachtenberg errs
language phase shift i don't think we
can quite fathom what is coming when we
start to merge all of the latest social
technologies and physical technologies
and elevated states of consciousness
together into a new more new model and
so I think um I think is going to
get really real and I think one lens to
look at that is to kind of close up and
say the worlds are gonna end on another
way to look at that is to this this is a
massive opportunity for us to step into
quite literally the next phase of our
species evolution
or die trying or die trying yeah at the
same time I just think again it's this
paradox in this necessity to hold both
the Steven Pinker partial truth chamber
new partial truths were collapsing and
were innovating and what we're going to
emerge into like you know we're in this
birth canal and we're kicking and
screaming and it's very you know Stan
Grof is having a great time thinking
like what is what is happening the
collective psyche right now we're can
event to use REM BPM 3 we're in we're in
this deep state of were think we're
gonna die and in BPM 3jv era you know
BPM 3 is like standard actual matrix
perineum elephant I saw yeah but parents
are matrices of Stan Grof that says each
time we all go through like there are
four perinatal matrices is when you're
in the womb when you're about to come
out the room when you're being literally
coming out the womb and then when you
when you're free and psychedelic
experiences map onto those bpms we're in
this fighting with we don't want to be
the we don't want to move out from our
comfortable space were in that and I
just think we have to have trust that
the evolution of consciousness is so
ingenious that if we are lying with the
correct forces of evolution what is
going to emerge will be more beautiful
and yet it's going to hurt so
when I've left left behind the
catastrophes lens it's not because I
think it's all gonna be fairies and
butterflies but it's that there's just
more and more trust in the evolutionary
process of the cosmos yeah I'm struck by
I mean the direct references on the kind
of deep the more implicit references to
Richard tanis's work and I would
recommend now for anyone watching this
they haven't read it the epilogue to
passion of the Western mind where he
kind of lays out all of that and the
Stan Grof model and how Western
philosophy and Western thought has
has created the conditions to give birth
to the next thing and he frames that was
the return to the entirety of the return
to the feminine have you read that it is
amazing I'd say it's probably had as
much impact on me as anything I've ever
read yeah
bricks bricks a genius and it's not it's
not the west we have to leave behind
rationality lastly we have to synthesize
it with these deeply embodied ways of
knowing that can complement our abstract
of capacities yeah when we do that and
then you hybridize that with artificial
intelligence this is a new thing
emerging and I'm starting to trust in
that more mmm yeah yeah I think I feel
that just because whatever is going to
emerge is going to only emerge from
being able to tap into that still place
like collectively and individually where
it's going to emerge from panic takes us
completely out of the the place of
contact with that emergent space so it's
it's it's not gonna be the thing like if
we ever get to the point where we're
panicking being overwhelmed by it it's
not gonna we're not gonna make it from
there that's almost like that that makes
it a self-fulfilling prophecy the kind
of the determination narrative yeah yeah
that's interesting I mean from a
meditative perspective Trust is the key
ingredient in letting your experience
unfold in a way that allows it to
breathe such that you discover what is
being offered to you and so I think it's
it's perfect what you say that there's
this transition available to to trusting
it even in the messiness right even in
the possibility of
collapse of destruction there's some
beauty there oh yeah I love what you say
Joshua and to go back to she's just and
not trust this how do we cultivate and
stability in our own being I think when
stuff does start to break down people
are going to be searching for whether
they know or not game beers like what is
going on and where do we go and I think
to cultivate and being a pillar of
stability amidst the chaos is possibly
our greatest service to the world yeah I
think in terms of going local you
mentioned the word localism I think in
terms of our offering to our community
and this is a piece that I really want
to emphasize because of the impact is
out of my own life and because of the
what I've read in the literature is this
necessity of introducing a truth and
transparency into relationships that can
we as were pillars of stability also
start to encourage truthful and
transparent communication as much as
possible because I think one of the meta
and existential risk factors of our
times is actually this loss of truth
because it's a loss of sense making as
organisms if you can if you cannot sense
make in your environment and think about
it we're transitioning more from
physical space to digital space digital
space propaganda fake news exponential
eyes disinformation as Daniel Shmack
says that's an existential risk factor
and what can we do were powerless with
regard to social media but can we create
containers of trust through truth so
that when stuff starts to happen we have
our boys and girls and we can trust for
me Trust is Z comes from from
truthfulness
yeah sure like where feels like a quite
a nice place to wrap up because you just
bookmarks it by referring back to tinker
and Bendele that's kind of stuff which
is we said the beginning but I'm just
before we do is there anything more than
coming up for you that no I just so
appreciate getting to hear you're
thinking about this more Joshua I think
it's a bit eerie to me how much what
you're saying aligns with how I what
I've come to feel about what we've been
talking about and I feel a kind of
resonance and some level of like
validation or kind of encouragement from
that a little bit then if there's a part
of me that's also like cautious like we
were drinking the same kool-aid but yeah
now I love that I don't really need to
have very much so if you found that
conversation useful I'd highly recommend
checking out the films in our members
area with Jamie wheel that we recorded
at the recent workshop in London which
was called collective sense making in an
age of existential risk and is available
for members I'll run a short clip of
that now normally okay that kind of
powers reserved for a lunatic
jihadis right bent on destruction
animating from fear and hate what's
possible if we can initiate ourselves
enjoy and love all right it's the
samurai notion of meditate on the
thousand waves you may die so that when
it comes times take your stand on the
field you do not flinch and that's not
McCobb that's not morbid that is not a
death wish
paradoxically having no regrets having
no hesitation knowing what my life is
for actually massively increases the
odds of us getting out of this in a good
way
and as always we can only keep making
these films with your help
so if you're enjoying them please do
consider becoming a member join in the
community we're doing a lot more Q&A
calls with the people in our films and
building up much more of an online
community now in 2020 so look forward to
seeing you soon